We have a global health challenge
هناك تحدّ للصحة العالمية
in our hands today,
يقف أمامنا اليوم،
and that is that the way we currently
وهو حول كيفية اكتشافنا
discover and develop new drugs
و تطويرنا للعقاقير حاليا
is too costly, takes far too long,
بطريقة مكلفة جدّا، تستغرق وقتا طويلا،
and it fails more often than it succeeds.
و فشلها أكثر من نجاحها.
It really just isn't working, and that means
إنّ الأمر لا يعمل كما ينبغي، ممّا يعني
that patients that badly need new therapies
أنّ المرضى المحتاجين بإلحاح لعلاجات جديدة
are not getting them,
لن يجدوا ما يحتاجونه،
and diseases are going untreated.
و أنّ الأمراض لن تعالج.
We seem to be spending more and more money.
و نحن أيضا ننفق كميات متزايدة من الأموال.
So for every billion dollars we spend in R&amp;D,
على كلّ مليار دولار ننفقه على البحث و التطوير،
we're getting less drugs approved into the market.
نحن نحصل على عدد أقل من الأدوية المصادق عليها للتسويق.
More money, less drugs. Hmm.
أمصاريف أكثر أدوية أقل , هممم
So what's going on here?
إذن ما الخطب هنا؟
Well, there's a multitude of factors at play,
حسنا، هناك العديد من العوامل،
but I think one of the key factors
لكن أعقتد أنّ واحدا من أهمّها هو
is that the tools that we currently have
كون الوسائل التي نمتلكها حاليّا
available to test whether a drug is going to work,
التي نستعملها لاختبار مدى فعالية دواء ما
whether it has efficacy,
ما إن كان ناجعا أم لا،
or whether it's going to be safe
و ما إن كان آمنا للاستعمال
before we get it into human clinical trials,
قبل البدأ بتجربته اكلينيكيّا على البشر،
are failing us. They're not predicting
تخذلنا. إنّها لا تتنبّؤ
what's going to happen in humans.
بما سيحصل للبشر.
And we have two main tools available
و لنا وسيلتان رئيسيتان
at our disposal.
متاحتان للاستعمال.
They are cells in dishes and animal testing.
الخلايا في الصفائح و الاختبار على الحيوانات.
Now let's talk about the first one, cells in dishes.
لنتحّدث في البدأ عن الأولى، الخلايا في الصفائح.
So, cells are happily functioning in our bodies.
تعمل الخلايا بطريقة طبيعية في أجسادنا،
We take them and rip them out
نقوم باستخراجها
of their native environment, throw them in one of these dishes,
من بيئتها الأصلية، نرميها إلى إحدى هذه الأطباق،
and expect them to work.
ثمّ نتوقّع منها العمل.
Guess what. They don't.
لكنها لا تفعل.
They don't like that environment
إنّها لا تحبّذ تلك البيئة
because it's nothing like
لأنّها لا تشبه أبدا
what they have in the body.
البيئة التي تعيش فيها داخل الجسم.
What about animal testing?
ماذا عن التجارب على الحيوانات؟
Well, animals do and can provide
إنّ الحيوانات تستطيع أن توفّر
extremely useful information.
معلومات مفيدة و هو ما تفعله بالفعل.
They teach us about what happens
إنّها تعلّمنا عمّا يحدث
in the complex organism.
داخل الكائن المعقّد.
We learn more about the biology itself.
نحن نتعلّم أكثر عن البيولوجيا نفسها.
However, more often than not,
لكن في الغالب،
animal models fail to predict what will happen in humans
النماذج الحيوانية تفشل في التنبّؤ بما سيحدث عند البشر
when they're treated with a particular drug.
عند معالجتها بدواء ما.
So we need better tools.
إذن فنحن نحتاج وسائل أفضل.
We need human cells,
نحن نحتاج خلايا بشرية
but we need to find a way to keep them happy
لكن علينا إيجاد طريقة لتركها تعمل بسعادة
outside the body.
خارج الجسم.
Our bodies are dynamic environments.
إنّ أجسامنا بيئات حيوية.
We're in constant motion.
إنّها في حركة مستمرّة.
Our cells experience that.
و خلايانا تختبر ذلك.
They're in dynamic environments in our body.
إنّها تعيش في الأوساط الديناميكية داخل أجسامنا.
They're under constant mechanical forces.
وهي تتأثّر بقوى ميكانيكية مستمرة.
So if we want to make cells happy
لذا فإن أردنا جعل الخلايا سعيدة
outside our bodies,
خارج الجسم
we need to become cell architects.
فعلينا أن نصبح مهندسي خلايا.
We need to design, build and engineer
علينا أن نصمّم و نبني و نهندس
a home away from home for the cells.
موطنا خارج الجسم للخلايا.
And at the Wyss Institute,
و في معهد فيس،
we've done just that.
هذا هو تماما ما قمنا به.
We call it an organ-on-a-chip.
نحن نسمّيها "عضو على رقاقة".
And I have one right here.
ولي واحدة منها هنا،
It's beautiful, isn't it? But it's pretty incredible.
إنّها جميلة، أليس كذلك؟ الأمر لا يصدّق.
Right here in my hand is a breathing, living
هنا تماما في يدي هناك رئة بشريّة
human lung on a chip.
حيّة تتنفّس في رقاقة.
And it's not just beautiful.
إنّه أمر أكثر من جميل.
It can do a tremendous amount of things.
وهو أمر يمكنه أن يقوم بعديد الأشياء.
We have living cells in that little chip,
لدينا خلايا حيّة في تلك الرقاقة الصّغيرة،
cells that are in a dynamic environment
الخلايا الموجودة في بيئة ديناميكية
interacting with different cell types.
تتفاعل مع مختلف أنواع الخلايا.
There's been many people
كان هناك عدد كبير من النّاس
trying to grow cells in the lab.
يحاولون تنمية خلايا في المختبر.
They've tried many different approaches.
لقد حاولوا بشتّى الطّرق.
They've even tried to grow little mini-organs in the lab.
وصلوا إلى درجة محاولة تنمية أعضاء مصغّرة في المختبر.
We're not trying to do that here.
لن نحاول القيام بذلك مجدّدا.
We're simply trying to recreate
نحن فقط بصدد إعادة صنع
in this tiny chip
في هذه الرّقاقة الصّغيرة
the smallest functional unit
أصغر وحدة وظيفيّة
that represents the biochemistry,
تمثيليّة للبيوكيمياء،
the function and the mechanical strain
الوظيفة و التّسلسل الميكانيكيّ
that the cells experience in our bodies.
الذي تعيشه الخلايا داخل أجسامنا.
So how does it work? Let me show you.
فكيف يعمل هذا؟ دعوني أريكم.
We use techniques from the computer chip
نستعمل تقنيات من الصناعة التحويلية
manufacturing industry
لرقاقات الحاسوب
to make these structures at a scale
لصنع هذه الهياكل ذات المقياس
relevant to both the cells and their environment.
المناسب للخلايا و لبيئتها.
We have three fluidic channels.
لدينا ثلاثة قنوات سوائل.
In the center, we have a porous, flexible membrane
في المركز، هناك غشاء مشاميّ مرن
on which we can add human cells
يمكن من خلاله إضافة الخلايا البشريّة
from, say, our lungs,
من الرئتين مثلا،
and then underneath, they had capillary cells,
و أسفلها هناك خلايا الشعيرات الدموية،
the cells in our blood vessels.
وهي الخلايا بأوعيتنا الدموية.
And we can then apply mechanical forces to the chip
ثمّ نستطيع بعد ذلك تسليط قوى ميكانيكية على الرقاقة
that stretch and contract the membrane,
فتجعل الغشاء يتمدّد و يتقلّص،
so the cells experience the same mechanical forces
إذن تختبر الخلايا نفس القوى الميكانيكية
that they did when we breathe.
التي تحصل عندما نتنفّس.
And they experience them how they did in the body.
و هي تجربة مشابهة لما تعيشه في الجسد.
There's air flowing through the top channel,
هناك هواء يمرّ عبر القناة العلوية،
and then we flow a liquid that contains nutrients
ثمّ نسكب سائلا يحتوي على مغذّيات
through the blood channel.
إلى القناة الدموية.
Now the chip is really beautiful,
الرقاقة تبدو جميلة فعلا،
but what can we do with it?
لكن ما الذي يمكننا القيام به بواسطتها؟
We can get incredible functionality
نستطيع التحصل على وظيفيّة جيّدة
inside these little chips.
داخل هذه الرّقاقات الصغيرة.
Let me show you.
دعوني أريكم.
We could, for example, mimic infection,
يمكن مثلا محاكاة العدوى،
where we add bacterial cells into the lung.
حيث نضيف خلايا بكتيرية إلى الرئة
then we can add human white blood cells.
ثمّ نضيف كريات دم بيضاء بشريّة.
White blood cells are our body's defense
الكريات البيضاء هي ما يدافع عن جسمنا
against bacterial invaders,
ضدّ البكتيريا الدخيلة،
and when they sense this inflammation due to infection,
و عندما تحسّ بهذا الالتهاب الذي تسبّبت فيه العدوى،
they will enter from the blood into the lung
سوف تدخل من الدّم إلى الرئة
and engulf the bacteria.
و تبتلع البكتيريا.
Well now you're going to see this happening
حسنا سترون الأمر أثناء حدوثه الآن
live in an actual human lung on a chip.
مباشرة من رئة بشريّة في رقاقة.
We've labeled the white blood cells so you can see them flowing through,
لقد قمنا بتمييز كريات الدم البيضاء حتّى تتمكّنوا من رؤيتها بوضوح،
and when they detect that infection,
و عندما تكشف عن العدوى،
they begin to stick.
فهي تبدأ بالالتصاق.
They stick, and then they try to go into the lung
ثمّ تحاول الذهاب إلى جانب
side from blood channel.
الرئة عبر القناة الدموية.
And you can see here, we can actually visualize
و تستطيعون أن تروا هنا، بامكاننا تصوير
a single white blood cell.
خلية الدم البيضاء فرديّا.
It sticks, it wiggles its way through
إنّها تلتصق و تتلوّى طيلة الطريق
between the cell layers, through the pore,
بين طبقات الخلايا، عبر المسامات
comes out on the other side of the membrane,
و تخرج من الجهة الأخرى من الغشاء
and right there, it's going to engulf the bacteria
و هنا تماما، سوف تقوم بابتلاع البكتيريا
labeled in green.
الملوّنة بالأخضر.
In that tiny chip, you just witnessed
لقد شاهدتهم لتوّكم في هذه الرقاقة الصغيرة
one of the most fundamental responses
إحدى ردات الفعل الرئيسية
our body has to an infection.
لجسمنا تجاه العدوى.
It's the way we respond to -- an immune response.
إنّها طريقة استجابتنا -- استجابة مناعيّة.
It's pretty exciting.
إنّه أمر مشوّق.
Now I want to share this picture with you,
أرغب في مشاركة هذه الصورة معكم،
not just because it's so beautiful,
ليس فقط لجمالها الشديد
but because it tells us an enormous amount of information
بل لأنّها تنقل لنا كمية هائلة من المعلومات
about what the cells are doing within the chips.
عمّا تفعله الخلايا داخل الرقاقات.
It tells us that these cells
إنّها تخبرنا أنّّ هذه الخلايا
from the small airways in our lungs,
من المسارات الهوائية في رئتينا
actually have these hairlike structures
بها هياكل مشابهة للشعر
that you would expect to see in the lung.
تتوقّع رؤيتها في الرّئات.
These structures are called cilia,
هذه الهياكل تسمّى أهدابا،
and they actually move the mucus out of the lung.
وهي قادرة على تحريك المخاط نحو خارج الرئة.
Yeah. Mucus. Yuck.
نعم، مخاط. مقزّز.
But mucus is actually very important.
لكن المخاط في الواقع هامّ جدّا.
Mucus traps particulates, viruses,
المخاط يحبس الجزيئات و الفيروسات
potential allergens,
و المواد التي قد تسبّب الحساسية
and these little cilia move
و هذه الأهداب الصغيرة تحرّك
and clear the mucus out.
و تخرج المخاط من الرّئة.
When they get damaged, say,
في حال تضرّرها،
by cigarette smoke for example,
بسبب التّدخين مثلا،
they don't work properly, and they can't clear that mucus out.
لن تتمكّن من العمل كما ينبغي، و لن تتمكّن من اخراج المخاط.
And that can lead to diseases such as bronchitis.
وهو ما قد يسبّب الإصابة بأمراض مثل الالتهاب الشّعبيّ الحادّ.
Cilia and the clearance of mucus
الأهداب و إخراج المخاط مرتبطة
are also involved in awful diseases like cystic fibrosis.
أيضا بأمراض خطيرة مثل التليف الكيسي.
But now, with the functionality that we get in these chips,
لكن الآن، من خلال القيمة الوظيفية التي نتحصّل عليها من خلال هذه الرّقاقات،
we can begin to look
نستطيع أن نبدأ بالبحث
for potential new treatments.
عن طرق جديدة ممكنة للعلاج.
We didn't stop with the lung on a chip.
لم يتوقّف الأمر مع الرئة في رقاقة.
We have a gut on a chip.
لدينا أمعاء في رقاقة.
You can see one right here.
يمكنكم رؤية واحدة منها هنا.
And we've put intestinal human cells
لقد وضعنا الخلايا المعوية البشرية
in a gut on a chip,
في رقاقة،
and they're under constant peristaltic motion,
و هي في بيئة ذات حركة احتوائية متواصلة، حركة
this trickling flow through the cells,
هذا السيلان المتقطّر عبر الخلايا،
and we can mimic many of the functions
و نستطيع محاكاة عديد الوظائف
that you actually would expect to see
التي قد تتوقّع من الأمعاء البشرية
in the human intestine.
القيام بها.
Now we can begin to create models of diseases
نستطيع الآن البدأ في صنع نماذج من الأمراض
such as irritable bowel syndrome.
مثل متلازمة القولون المتهيج.
This is a disease that affects
إنّه مرض يصيب
a large number of individuals.
عددا كبيرا من الأشخاص.
It's really debilitating,
إنّه فعلا موهن،
and there aren't really many good treatments for it.
و ليس هناك أيّة علاجات فعالة ضدّه.
Now we have a whole pipeline
الآن لدينا خط أنابيب كاملا
of different organ chips
لمختلف رقاقات الأعضاء
that we are currently working on in our labs.
التي نعمل عليها في مختبراتنا.
Now, the true power of this technology, however,
لكن القوة الحقيقة لهذه التكنولوجيا
really comes from the fact
تكمن في حقيقة كوننا نستطيع
that we can fluidically link them.
وصلها ببعضها البعض عبر السوائل.
There's fluid flowing across these cells,
هناك سائل يعوم حول هذه الخلايا،
so we can begin to interconnect
إذن يمكننا جعل مختلف الرقاقات
multiple different chips together
تتفاعل مع بعضها البعض
to form what we call a virtual human on a chip.
لتكوين ما نسمّيه بإنسان افتراضي في رقاقة.
Now we're really getting excited.
الآن نحن متحمسون جدا.
We're not going to ever recreate a whole human in these chips,
لن نقوم أبدا بإعادة خلق بشريّ كامل في هذه الرقاقات،
but what our goal is is to be able to recreate
لكن هدفنا هو إعادة خلق
sufficient functionality
وظيفيّة كافية
so that we can make better predictions
تمكّننا من التنبؤ بطريقة أفضل
of what's going to happen in humans.
عمّا سيحدث داخل البشر.
For example, now we can begin to explore
مثلا يمكننا البدأ في اكتشاف
what happens when we put a drug like an aerosol drug.
ماذا يحدث عند وضع دواء مثل الدواء الضبابيّ.
Those of you like me who have asthma, when you take your inhaler,
بالنسبة لمن يعانون منكم من الربو مثلي، عندما تأخذون دواء الاستنشاق
we can explore how that drug comes into your lungs,
نستطيع اكتشاف كيفية عمل ذلك الدواء بالرئتين،
how it enters the body,
كيفية دخوله الجسم
how it might affect, say, your heart.
و كيف يمكنه التأثير على قلبك مثلا.
Does it change the beating of your heart?
هل يقوم بتغيير معدل نبضات القلب؟
Does it have a toxicity?
هل فيه مواد سامة؟
Does it get cleared by the liver?
هل يتم تصفيتها عبر الكبد؟
Is it metabolized in the liver?
هل يتم استقلابها في الكبد؟
Is it excreted in your kidneys?
هل يتم إفرازها في الكلى؟
We can begin to study the dynamic
نستطيع البدأ بدراسة الاستجابة
response of the body to a drug.
الديناميكية للجسد تجاه دواء ما.
This could really revolutionize
هذا من شأنه أن يحدث ثورة
and be a game changer
و نقلة نوعية
for not only the pharmaceutical industry,
ليس فقط للصناعة الصيدلية
but a whole host of different industries,
بل للعديد من الصناعات الأخرى
including the cosmetics industry.
منها صناعة مواد التجميل.
We can potentially use the skin on a chip
نستطيع استعمال الجلد في الرقاقة
that we're currently developing in the lab
وهو ما نقوم حاليا بتطويره في المختبر
to test whether the ingredients in those products
لتجربة ما إن كانت المكونات في هذه المنتجات
that you're using are actually safe to put on your skin
التي تستعملونها حاليا آمنة لوضعها على بشرتك
without the need for animal testing.
دون الحاجة للتجربة على الحيوان.
We could test the safety
نستطيع امتحان سلامة
of chemicals that we are exposed to
المواد الكيميائية التي نحن عرضة لها
on a daily basis in our environment,
بشكل يومي في البيئة التي نعيش فيها،
such as chemicals in regular household cleaners.
مثل الكيميائيات الموجودة في مواد التنظيف المنزلية العادية.
We could also use the organs on chips
نستطيع أيضا استعمال الأعضاء في الرقاقة
for applications in bioterrorism
للتطبيقات في الارهاب البيولوجي
or radiation exposure.
أو التعرض الإشعاعي.
We could use them to learn more about
كما نستطيع استعمالها لتعلّم المزيد عن
diseases such as ebola
الأمراض مثل الإيبولا
or other deadly diseases such as SARS.
أو أمراضا قاتلة أخرى كفيروس سارس.
Organs on chips could also change
الأعضاء في الرقاقات بامكانها أيضا تغيير
the way we do clinical trials in the future.
طريقة القيام بالتجارب الاكلينيكية مستقبلا.
Right now, the average participant
حاليا فإنّ المشارك العادي
in a clinical trial is that: average.
في التجارب الاكلينيكية هو شخص نمطيّ.
Tends to be middle aged, tends to be female.
إذ أنّه يميل لأن يكون أنثى في منتصف العمر.
You won't find many clinical trials
لن تجد الكثير من التجارب الاكلينيكية
in which children are involved,
شارك فيها أطفال
yet every day, we give children medications,
و رغم ذلك فإنّنا نعطي الأطفال الأدوية يوميا
and the only safety data we have on that drug
و المعلومة الوحيدة الآمنة التي نمتلكها عن ذلك الدواء
is one that we obtained from adults.
كنّا قد تحصلنا عليها من البالغين.
Children are not adults.
الأطفال ليسوا ببالغين.
They may not respond in the same way adults do.
إنّهم لا يستجيبون بنفس طريقة استجابة البالغين.
There are other things like genetic differences
هناك عوامل أخرى مثل الاختلافات الجينية
in populations
في الشعوب
that may lead to at-risk populations
التي قد تتسّب في جعل شعب كامل
that are at risk of having an adverse drug reaction.
عرضة لخطر الاستجابة بطريقة سلبية للدواء.
Now imagine if we could take cells from all those different populations,
تخيّلوا لو استطعنا أخذ خلايا من مختلف الشعوب
put them on chips,
وضعها في رقاقات
and create populations on a chip.
و إحداث شعوب في الرقاقات.
This could really change the way
هذا يستطيع فعلا أن يغيّر طريقة
we do clinical trials.
قيامنا بالتجارب الاكلينيكية.
And this is the team and the people that are doing this.
وهذا هو الفريق و الأشخاص الذين يقومون بهذا كلّه.
We have engineers, we have cell biologists,
معنا مهندسون و بيولوجيو خلايا
we have clinicians, all working together.
وأطباء سريريّين، كلّهم يعملون معا.
We're really seeing something quite incredible
نحن نرى فعلا أمرا مذهلا
at the Wyss Institute.
في معهد فيس.
It's really a convergence of disciplines,
إنّها فعلا نقطة التقاء التخصّصات
where biology is influencing the way we design,
حيث البيولوجيا تؤثّر في طريقة تصميمنا،
the way we engineer, the way we build.
طريقة هندستنا و بناءنا.
It's pretty exciting.
أنّه أمر حماسيّ.
We're establishing important industry collaborations
نحن نؤسّس لتعاون صناعيّ هام
such as the one we have with a company
مثل العلاقة التي تجمعنا مع شركة
that has expertise in large-scale digital manufacturing.
التي لها خبرة في الصناعة الرقمية الضخمة.
They're going to help us make,
وهم سيقومون بمساعدتنا على صنع،
instead of one of these,
عوض واحدة من هذه
millions of these chips,
ملايين من الرقاقات
so that we can get them into the hands
حتّى نتمكّن من إعطائها إلى
of as many researchers as possible.
أكبر عدد ممكن من الباحثين.
And this is key to the potential of that technology.
وهذا أمر هامّ جدا لمدى نجاح هذه التكنولوجيا.
Now let me show you our instrument.
دعوني أريكم أداتنا.
This is an instrument that our engineers
هذه أداة يعمل مهندسونا
are actually prototyping right now in the lab,
على نمذجتها حاليّا في المختبر،
and this instrument is going to give us
و هذه الأداة قادرة على توفير
the engineering controls that we're going to require
التحكم الهندسيّ الذي نحتاجه
in order to link 10 or more organ chips together.
لوصل 10 أو أكثر من رقاقات الأعضاء ببعضها البعض.
It does something else that's very important.
وهي تقوم بأمر آخر في غاية الأهمية.
It creates an easy user interface.
إنّها تصنع واجهة استعمال سهلة.
So a cell biologist like me can come in,
بيولوجيّ خلايا مثلي يمكنه القدوم
take a chip, put it in a cartridge
أخذ رقاقة، وضعها في خرطوشة
like the prototype you see there,
مثل النموذج الأولي هناك،
put the cartridge into the machine
وضع الخرطوشة في الآلة
just like you would a C.D.,
تماما كما تفعل مع أقراص الليزر
and away you go.
و يمكنك البدأ.
Plug and play. Easy.
توصلها و تشغّلها. الأمر سهل.
Now, let's imagine a little bit
دعونا نتخيّل قليلا
what the future might look like
عمّا سيكون عليه المستقبل
if I could take your stem cells
إن قمت بأخذ خلاياك الجذعية
and put them on a chip,
و وضعتها في رقاقة
or your stem cells and put them on a chip.
أو وضعت خلاياك الجذعية في رقاقة.
It would be a personalized chip just for you.
سوف تصبح الرقاقة خاصة بك.
Now all of us in here are individuals,
كلّ منّا هو فرد
and those individual differences mean
و كلّ هذه الاختلافات الفردية تعني
that we could react very differently
أنّ بامكاننا الاستجابة بطرق مختلفة للأدوية
and sometimes in unpredictable ways to drugs.
و بطرق غير متوقّعة أيضا في بعض الأحيان.
I myself, a couple of years back, had a really bad headache,
كنت أعاني من صداع رهيب جدّا منذ سنوات مضت،
just couldn't shake it, thought, "Well, I'll try something different."
لم أتمكّن من التّغلب عليه، ففكّرت: "حسنا، سأقوم بتجربة أمر مختلف."
I took some Advil. Fifteen minutes later,
لقد تعاطيت دواء الأدفيل. و بعد 15 دقيقة،
I was on my way to the emergency room
كنت في طريقي نحو غرفة الطوارئ
with a full-blown asthma attack.
و أصبت بنوبة ربو حادّة.
Now, obviously it wasn't fatal,
من الواضح أنّ الأمر لم يكن قاتلا
but unfortunately, some of these
لكن لسوء الحظ بعض هذه الاستجابات
adverse drug reactions can be fatal.
السلبية للأدوية يمكن أن تكون مميتة.
So how do we prevent them?
فكيف نحول دون حدوثها؟
Well, we could imagine one day
حسنا، يمكننا تخيّل يوم ما
having Geraldine on a chip,
يكون لدينا فيه جيرالدين في رقاقة،
having Danielle on a chip,
أو دانيال في رقاقة،
having you on a chip.
أنت في رقاقة.
Personalized medicine. Thank you.
الطب المخصّص. شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)